Now, some of you might hear this and feel sad. After all, America is deeply invested in this idea of economic transcendence, that every generation kind of leapfrogs the one before it, earning more, buying more, being more. We've exported this dream all over the world, so kids in Brazil and China and even Kenya inherit our insatiable expectation for more. But when I read this historic poll for the first time, it didn't actually make me feel sad. It felt like a provocation. "Better off" -- based on whose standards? Is "better off" finding a secure job that you can count on for the rest of your life? Those are nearly extinct. People move jobs, on average, every 4.7 years, and it's estimated that by 2020, nearly half of Americans will be freelancers. OK, so is better off just a number? Is it about earning as much as you possibly can? By that singular measurement, we are failing. Median per capita income has been flat since about 2000, adjusted for inflation. All right, so is better off getting a big house with a white picket fence? Less of us are doing that. Nearly five million people lost their homes in the Great Recession, and even more of us sobered up about the lengths we were willing to go -- or be tricked into going, in many predatory cases -- to hold that deed. Home-ownership rates are at their lowest since 1995. All right, so we're not finding steady employment, we're not earning as much money, and we're not living in big fancy houses. Toll the funeral bells for everything that made America great. But, are those the best measurements of a country's greatness, of a life well lived? What I think makes America great is its spirit of reinvention. In the wake of the Great Recession, more and more Americans are redefining what "better off" really means. Turns out, it has more to do with community and creativity than dollars and cents. Now, let me be very clear: the 14.8 percent of Americans living in poverty need money, plain and simple. And all of us need policies that protect us from exploitation by employers and financial institutions. Nothing that follows is meant to suggest that the gap between rich and poor is anything but profoundly immoral. But, too often we let the conversation stop there. We talk about poverty as if it were a monolithic experience; about the poor as if they were solely victims. Part of what I've learned in my research and reporting is that the art of living well is often practiced most masterfully by the most vulnerable. Now, if necessity is the mother of invention, I've come to believe that recession can be the father of consciousness. It confronts us with profound questions, questions we might be too lazy or distracted to ask in times of relative comfort. How should we work? How should we live? All of us, whether we realize it or not, seek answers to these questions, with our ancestors kind of whispering in our ears. My great-grandfather was a drunk in Detroit, who sometimes managed to hold down a factory job. He had, as unbelievable as it might sound, 21 children, with one woman, my great-grandmother, who died at 47 years old of ovarian cancer. Now, I'm pregnant with my second child, and I cannot even fathom what she must have gone through. And if you're trying to do the math -- there were six sets of twins. So my grandfather, their son, became a traveling salesman, and he lived boom and bust. So my dad grew up answering the door for debt collectors and pretending his parents weren't home. He actually took his braces off himself with pliers in the garage, when his father admitted he didn't have money to go back to the orthodontist. So my dad, unsurprisingly, became a bankruptcy lawyer. Couldn't write this in a novel, right? He was obsessed with providing a secure foundation for my brother and I. So I ask these questions by way of a few generations of struggle. My parents made sure that I grew up on a kind of steady ground that allows one to question and risk and leap. And ironically, and probably sometimes to their frustration, it is their steadfast commitment to security that allows me to question its value, or at least its value as we've historically defined it in the 21st century. So let's dig into this first question: How should we work? We should work like our mothers. That's right -- we've spent decades trying to fit women into a work world built for company men. And many have done backbends to fit in, but others have carved a more unconventional path, creating a patchwork of meaning and money with enough flexibility to do what they need to do for those that they love. My mom called it "just making it work." Today I hear life coaches call it "a portfolio career." Whatever you call it, more and more men are craving these whole, if not harried, lives. They're waking up to their desire and duty to be present fathers and sons. Now, artist Ann Hamilton has said, "Labor is a way of knowing." Labor is a way of knowing. In other words, what we work on is what we understand about the world. If this is true, and I think it is, then women who have disproportionately cared for the little ones and the sick ones and the aging ones, have disproportionately benefited from the most profound kind of knowing there is: knowing the human condition. By prioritizing care, men are, in a sense, staking their claim to the full range of human existence. Now, this means the nine-to-five no longer works for anyone. Punch clocks are becoming obsolete, as are career ladders. Whole industries are being born and dying every day. It's all nonlinear from here. So we need to stop asking kids, "What do you want to be when you grow up?" and start asking them, "How do you want to be when you grow up?" Their work will constantly change. The common denominator is them. So the more they understand their gifts and create crews of ideal collaborators, the better off they will be. The challenge ahead is to reinvent the social safety net to fit this increasingly fragmented economy. We need portable health benefits. We need policies that reflect that everyone deserves to be vulnerable or care for vulnerable others, without becoming destitute. We need to seriously consider a universal basic income. We need to reinvent labor organizing. The promise of a work world that is structured to actually fit our 21st century values, not some archaic idea about bringing home the bacon, is long overdue -- just ask your mother. Now, how about the second question: How should we live? We should live like our immigrant ancestors. When they came to America, they often shared apartments, survival tactics, child care -- always knew how to fill one more belly, no matter how small the food available. But they were told that success meant leaving the village behind and pursuing that iconic symbol of the American Dream, the white picket fence. And even today, we see a white picket fence and we think success, self-possession. But when you strip away the sentimentality, what it really does is divides us. Many Americans are rejecting the white picket fence and the kind of highly privatized life that happened within it, and reclaiming village life, reclaiming interdependence instead. Fifty million of us, for example, live in intergenerational households. This number exploded with the Great Recession, but it turns out people actually like living this way. Two-thirds of those who are living with multiple generations under one roof say it's improved their relationships. Some people are choosing to share homes not with family, but with other people who understand the health and economic benefits of daily community. CoAbode, an online platform for single moms looking to share homes with other single moms, has 50,000 users. And people over 65 are especially prone to be looking for these alternative living arrangements. They understand that their quality of life depends on a mix of solitude and solidarity. Which is true of all of us when you think about it, young and old alike. For too long, we've pretended that happiness is a king in his castle. But all the research proves otherwise. It shows that the healthiest, happiest and even safest -- in terms of both climate change disaster, in terms of crime, all of that -- are Americans who live lives intertwined with their neighbors. Now, I've experienced this firsthand. For the last few years, I've been living in a cohousing community. It's 1.5 acres of persimmon trees, this prolific blackberry bush that snakes around a community garden, all smack-dab, by the way, in the middle of urban Oakland. The nine units are all built to be different, different sizes, different shapes, but they're meant to be as green as possible. So big, shiny black solar cells on our roof mean our electricity bill rarely exceeds more than five bucks in a month. The 25 of us who live there are all different ages and political persuasions and professions, and we live in homes that have everything a typical home would have. But additionally, we share an industrial-sized kitchen and eating area, where we have common meals twice a week. Now, people, when I tell them I live like this, often have one of two extreme reactions. Either they say, "Why doesn't everyone live like this?" Or they say, "That sounds totally horrifying. I would never want to do that." So let me reassure you: there is a sacred respect for privacy among us, but also a commitment to what we call "radical hospitality" -- not the kind advertised by the Four Seasons, but the kind that says that every single person is worthy of kindness, full stop, end of sentence. The biggest surprise for me of living in a community like this? You share all the domestic labor -- the repairing, the cooking, the weeding -- but you also share the emotional labor. Rather than depending only on the idealized family unit to get all of your emotional needs met, you have two dozen other people that you can go to to talk about a hard day at work or troubleshoot how to handle an abusive teacher. Teenagers in our community will often go to an adult that is not their parent to ask for advice. It's what bell hooks called "revolutionary parenting," this humble acknowledgment that kids are healthier when they have a wider range of adults to emulate and count on. Turns out, adults are healthier, too. It's a lot of pressure, trying to be that perfect family behind that white picket fence. The "new better off," as I've come to call it, is less about investing in the perfect family and more about investing in the imperfect village, whether that's relatives living under one roof, a cohousing community like mine, or just a bunch of neighbors who pledge to really know and look out for one another. It's good common sense, right? And yet, money has often made us dumb about reaching out. The most reliable wealth is found in relationship. The new better off is not an individual prospect at all. In fact, if you're a failure or you think you're a failure, I've got some good news for you: you might be a success by standards you have not yet honored. Maybe you're a mediocre earner but a masterful father. Maybe you can't afford your dream home, but you throw legendary neighborhood parties. If you're a textbook success, the implications of what I'm saying could be more grim for you. You might be a failure by standards you hold dear but that the world doesn't reward. Only you can know. I know that I am not a tribute to my great-grandmother, who lived such a short and brutish life, if I earn enough money to afford every creature comfort. You can't buy your way out of suffering or into meaning. There is no home big enough to erase the pain that she must have endured. I am a tribute to her if I live a life as connected and courageous as possible. In the midst of such widespread uncertainty, we may, in fact, be insecure. But we can let that insecurity make us brittle or supple. We can turn inward, lose faith in the power of institutions to change -- even lose faith in ourselves. Or we can turn outward, cultivate faith in our ability to reach out, to connect, to create. Turns out, the biggest danger is not failing to achieve the American Dream. The biggest danger is achieving a dream that you don't actually believe in. So don't do that. Do the harder, more interesting thing, which is to compose a life where what you do every single day, the people you give your best love and ingenuity and energy to, aligns as closely as possible with what you believe. That, not something as mundane as making money, is a tribute to your ancestors. That is the beautiful struggle. Thank you. (Applause)
Algunos de Uds. al escuchar esto se sentirán tristes. Después de todo, EE.UU. está profundamente dedicado a esta idea de superación económica, en la que las generaciones deben ser "mejores" a la anterior, ganar más, comprar más, ser más. Hemos exportado este sueño por todo el mundo, así niños en Brasil y China, e incluso Kenia, heredan nuestra expectativa insaciable de querer más. Pero cuando leí esta encuesta histórica por primera vez, en realidad no me entristeció. Lo sentí como una provocación. "Mejores"... ¿según qué estándar? ¿Es "mejor" encontrar un empleo seguro donde permanecer el resto de la vida? Esos empleos casi no existen. La gente cambia de empleo, cada 4.7 años de promedio. Y se estima que para el 2020, cerca de la mitad de los estadounidenses trabajarán por cuenta propia. Bien, ¿"mejor" es solo un número? ¿Se trata de ganar tanto como posible? Por esa medición singular cometemos errores. El ingreso medio per capita ha sido igual desde el 2000, ajustado por la inflación. Así, ¿"mejor" es conseguir una gran casa con una cerca blanca? Pocos lo logran. Casi cinco millones de personas perdieron sus hogares en la Gran Recesión, y muchos enfrentamos seriamente hasta lo indecible o nos engañaron, y en muchos casos nos depredaron, para sostener esa proeza. Las tasas de propiedad de vivienda están en el nivel más bajo desde 1995. Es decir, no estamos encontrando un trabajo estable, no estamos ganando tanto dinero, y no estamos viviendo en grandes casas de lujo. Que doblen las campanas mortuorias para quienes hicieron grandes a EE.UU. Pero, ¿son esas las mejores mediciones de la grandeza de un país, de una vida bien vivida? Creo que lo que engrandece a EE.UU. es su espíritu de reinvención. Como consecuencia de la Gran Recesión, más y más estadounidenses redefinen qué significa "mejor". Resulta que tiene más que ver con la comunidad y la creatividad que con dólares y centavos. Pero seré clara: el 14.8 % de los estadounidenses que viven en la pobreza necesita dinero, simple y llanamente. Y nosotros necesitamos políticas que nos protejan de la explotación de los empleadores y las instituciones financieras. Que nada de lo que sigue oculte que la brecha entre ricos y pobres es algo profundamente inmoral. Pero, muy a menudo terminamos la conversación allí. Hablamos de la pobreza como si fuese una experiencia monolítica; y de los pobres como si fuesen exclusivamente víctimas. Parte de lo que he aprendido en mi investigación es que el arte de vivir bien a menudo se practica con más maestría entre los más vulnerables. Ahora, si la necesidad es la madre de la invención, he llegado a creer que la recesión es la madre de la conciencia. Eso nos confronta con preguntas profundas, preguntas que nos daría pereza o evitaríamos en momentos de relativa comodidad. ¿Cómo deberíamos trabajar? ¿Cómo deberíamos vivir? Todos, nos demos cuenta o no, buscamos respuestas a estas preguntas, en el susurro de nuestros antepasados repicándonos los oídos. Mi bisabuelo era un borracho de Detroit, que a veces lograba mantener un trabajo en la fábrica. Tuvo, por increíble que parezca, 21 hijos, con una mujer, mi bisabuela, que murió a los 47 años de cáncer de ovario. Ahora, estoy embarazada de mi segundo hijo, y ni siquiera puedo imaginar lo que debe haber pasado. Y si están tratando de calcular... había seis pares de gemelos. Así que mi abuelo, su hijo, se convirtió en un vendedor ambulante, y vivió el auge y la caída. Mi papá creció atendiendo en la puerta a los cobradores de deudas, fingiendo que sus padres no estaban en casa. Llegó a quitarse los brackets con pinzas en el garaje, cuando su padre admitió que no tenía dinero para volver al dentista. Así que mi padre, como era de esperar, se convirtió en un abogado de bancarrota. Podría escribir una novela, ¿verdad? Estaba obsesionado por darnos una base segura a mi hermano y a mí. Me hice estas preguntas en unas generaciones de lucha. Mis padres se aseguraron de que yo creciera en un terreno firme que me permitiera cuestionarme, arriesgar y saltar. E irónicamente, y probablemente a veces para su frustración, es su firme compromiso con la seguridad lo que me permite cuestionar su valor, o al menos su valor como lo hemos definido históricamente en el siglo XXI. Así que profundicemos en esta primera pregunta: ¿Cómo deberíamos trabajar? Deberíamos trabajar como nuestras madres. Así es, hemos pasado décadas tratando de encajar mujeres en un mundo de trabajo de hombres empresarios. Muchas han hecho esfuerzos para encajar, pero otras se han labrado un camino menos convencional, creando un mosaico de sentido y dinero con la suficiente flexibilidad para hacer lo que tienen que hacer para quienes aman. Mi mamá lo llamaba "simplemente hacer que funcione". Hoy escucho que lo llaman "un portfolio de carrera". Es igual cómo se llame, cada vez más hombres ansían vidas plenas, no acosadas. Albergan el deseo de ser padres e hijos presentes. La artista Ann Hamilton dijo: "El trabajo es una forma de conocer". El trabajo es una forma de conocer. En otras palabras, nuestro espacio de trabajo es lo que entendemos por mundo. Si esto es cierto, y creo que lo es, las mujeres que se han preocupado desproporcionadamente por sus pequeños, sus enfermos y sus ancianos, se han beneficiado desproporcionadamente del conocimiento más profundo existente: conocer la condición humana. Al dar prioridad al cuidado, los hombres, en cierto sentido, demandan la amplia gama de la existencia humana. Esto significa que el horario 9 a 17 ya no funciona para todos. Cumplir horarios se vuelve obsoleto, y también las escalas profesionales. Industrias enteras nacen y mueren todos los días. A partir de aquí, todo es no lineal. Por eso debemos dejar de preguntarle a los niños: "¿Qué quieres ser de mayor?" Y empezar a preguntarles: "¿Cómo quieres ser de mayor?" Su trabajo va a cambiar constantemente. El denominador común son ellos. Así que cuanto más conozcan sus dones y creen equipos de colaboradores ideales, "mejores" serán. El desafío es reinventar la red de seguridad social para adaptarse a esta creciente economía fragmentada. Necesitamos beneficios portátiles para la salud. Necesitamos políticas que reflejen que el mundo merece ser vulnerable o cuidar de otros vulnerables, sin llegar a la indigencia. Tenemos que considerar seriamente una renta básica universal. Tenemos que reinventar la organización del trabajo. La promesa de un mundo del trabajo estructurado para encajar nuestros valores del siglo XXI, no una idea arcaica de traer a casa el sustento, ya expiró hace tiempo... pregúntenle a sus madres. Ahora bien, ¿y la segunda pregunta? ¿Cómo debería vivir? Deberíamos vivir como los antepasados inmigrantes. Cuando llegaron a EE.UU., a menudo compartían apartamentos, tácticas de supervivencia, cuidado de niños, siempre sabían cómo saciar un estómago más, sin importar el alimento disponible. Pero les dijeron que el éxito era dejar atrás el pueblo y conseguir ese símbolo icónico del Sueño Americano, la cerca blanca. Y aún hoy, vemos una cerca blanca y la asociamos a éxito, a posesión. Pero dejando de lado el sentimentalismo, eso en realidad nos divide. Muchos estadounidenses rechazan la cerca blanca y el tipo de vida altamente privatizado que eso conlleva, y quieren recuperar la vida de pueblo, y la interdependencia, en cambio. 50 millones, por ejemplo, vivimos en hogares intergeneracionales. Este número explotó con la Gran Recesión, pero resulta que a la gente le gusta vivir así. Dos tercios de los que viven con varias generaciones bajo un mismo techo dicen que eso mejoró sus relaciones. Algunas personas optan por compartir hogares no con familiares, sino con otras personas que entienden los beneficios económicos y para la salud de la comunidad diaria. CoAbode, plataforma en línea para madres solteras que quieren compartir hogar con otras madres solteras, tiene 50 000 usuarias. Y las personas mayores de 65 años son especialmente propensas a buscar esas alternativas de vivienda. Entienden que su calidad de vida depende de una mezcla de soledad y solidaridad. Algo cierto para todos nosotros si lo piensan, jóvenes y ancianos por igual. Durante mucho tiempo, hemos fingido que la felicidad es un rey en su castillo. Pero toda la investigación demuestra lo contrario. Demuestra que los más sanos, los más felices e incluso los más seguros, en términos de cambio climático, delincuencia, todo eso, son los estadounidenses que viven vidas entrelazadas con sus vecinos. Ahora, he experimentado esto de primera mano. En los últimos años he vivido en una comunidad de vivienda cooperativa. Son 1,5 acres de árboles de caqui, este arbusto de moras que serpentea por un jardín de la comunidad, exactamente, por cierto, en medio del Oakland urbano. Las nueve unidades están construidas para ser diferentes, diferentes tamaños, diferentes formas, y lo más verdes posibles. Las grandes celdas solares negras y brillantes en los techos suponen que nuestra factura de la luz rara vez excede los USD 5 al mes. Las 25 personas que vivimos allí tenemos diferentes edades, tendencias políticas y profesiones, y vivimos en casas que tienen todo lo que tendría un hogar típico. Pero, además, compartimos una cocina y comedor de tamaño industrial, donde tenemos comidas en común dos veces por semana. Cuando cuento que vivo así a menudo veo dos reacciones extremas. O dicen: "¿Por qué no todo el mundo practica esto?" O dicen: "Suena horrible. No me gustaría hacer eso". Se los aseguro: hay un respeto sagrado por la privacidad entre nosotros, pero también un compromiso con lo que llamamos "hospitalidad radical", no la que anuncia Four Seasons, sino la que dice que cada persona es digna de bondad, punto final, final de la frase. ¿La mayor sorpresa para mí de vivir en una comunidad como esta? Uno comparte el trabajo doméstico, la reparación, la cocina, la escarda, pero también el trabajo emocional. En lugar de depender únicamente de la unidad familiar idealizada para satisfacer las necesidades emocionales, hay dos docenas de otras personas a los que acudir para hablar de un arduo día de trabajo o analizar cómo lidiar con un profesor abusivo. Los adolescentes de la comunidad suelen ir a un adulto que no es su padre en busca de consejo. Es lo que se llama "crianza revolucionaria", este humilde reconocimiento de que los niños son más saludables si tienen una gama más amplia de adultos para emular o en quien confiar. Resulta que los adultos son más saludables, también. Es mucha presión, tratar de ser esa familia perfecta detrás de la cerca blanca. El "nuevo mejor", como lo denomino, tiene que ver menos con la inversión en la familia perfecta y más con invertir en el pueblo imperfecto, ya sea con familiares que viven bajo un mismo techo, una comunidad de covivienda como la mía, o simplemente mucho vecinos que se comprometan a conocerse realmente y cuidarse unos a otros. Es de sentido común, ¿verdad? Y, sin embargo, el dinero a menudo nos ha confundido sobre lograr cosas. La riqueza más fiable se encuentra en la relación. El "nuevo mejor" no es una perspectiva individual en absoluto. De hecho, si Uds. son un fracaso o si creen ser un fracaso, tengo buenas noticias: podrían tener éxito en estándares que aún no conocen. Quizá uno tiene ingresos mediocres pero es un padre magistral. Quizá uno no puede permitirse el lujo de la casa de sus sueños, pero hace fiestas de barrio legendarias. Si uno tiene éxito con los libros, las consecuencias de lo que estoy diciendo, podrían ser más sombrías. Uno puede ser un fracaso en estándares que aprecia, pero que el mundo no recompensa. Solo uno puede saberlo. Sé que no soy un homenaje a mi bisabuela, que vivió una vida tan corta y brutal, al ganar suficiente dinero para pagar todas las comodidades. No se puede escapar al sufrimiento ni encontrar sentido. No hay algo lo suficientemente grande como para borrar el dolor que ella debe haber soportado. Soy un tributo a ella si vivo una vida tan conectada y valiente como sea posible. En medio de una incertidumbre generalizada, es posible que, de hecho, estemos inseguros. Pero podemos dejar que la inseguridad nos haga frágiles o flexibles. Podemos mirar hacia dentro, perder la fe en el cambio de las instituciones, incluso perder la fe en nosotros mismos. O podemos mirar hacia afuera, tener fe en nuestra capacidad de llegar, conectar, crear. Resulta que el mayor peligro no consiste en no cumplir el Sueño Americano. El mayor peligro es cumplir un sueño en el que uno en realidad no cree. No hagan eso. Hagan lo más difícil, lo más interesante, que es crear una vida en la que lo que hacen todos los días, las personas a las que les dan su amor, ingenio y energía, comparten lo más estrechamente posible lo que Uds. creen. Eso, no es algo tan mundano como ganar dinero, es un homenaje a sus antepasados. Esa es una lucha hermosa. Gracias. (Aplausos)